And how could they make scientific findings about my genes if I put down my social identity as a black woman? After all, I consider myself a black woman with a white father rather than a white woman with a black mother entirely for social reasons. Which racial identity I check has nothing to do with my genes. Well, despite the obvious importance of this question to the study's scientific validity, I was told, "Don't worry about it, just put down however you identify yourself." So I check "black," but I had no confidence in the results of a study that treated a critical variable so unscientifically. That personal experience with the use of race in genetic testing got me thinking: Where else in medicine is race used to make false biological predictions? Well, I found out that race runs deeply throughout all of medical practice.
¿Cómo podrían hacer hallazgos científicos sobre mis genes si ponía mi identidad social como mujer negra? Después de todo, me considero una mujer negra de padre blanco en lugar de una mujer blanca de madre negra debido completamente a razones sociales. La identidad racial que marco no tiene nada que ver con mis genes. Bueno, a pesar de la importancia obvia de esta pregunta para la validez científica del estudio, me dijeron: "No te preocupes por eso, solo pon lo que te identifique". Así que marqué "negra", pero no confiaba en los resultados de un estudio que trataba a una variable tan crucial de manera tan poco científica. Esa experiencia personal con el uso de la raza en pruebas genéticas me hizo pensar: ¿En qué otro ámbito de la medicina se usa la raza para hacer falsas predicciones biológicas? Bueno, encontré que la raza cala hondo en toda la práctica médica.
It shapes physicians' diagnoses, measurements, treatments, prescriptions, even the very definition of diseases. And the more I found out, the more disturbed I became. Sociologists like me have long explained that race is a social construction. When we identify people as black, white, Asian, Native American, Latina, we're referring to social groupings with made up demarcations that have changed over time and vary around the world. As a legal scholar, I've also studied how lawmakers, not biologists,
Conforma diagnósticos médicos, mediciones, tratamientos, recetas, incluso la propia definición de enfermedades. Y cuanto más descubría, más me perturbaba. Los sociólogos como yo han explicado extensamente que la raza es una construcción social. Cuando identificamos a la gente como negra, blanca, asiática, aborigen, latina, nos referimos a grupos sociales con delimitaciones inventadas que han cambiado con el tiempo y varían en todo el mundo. Como jurista también he estudiado cómo los legisladores, no los biólogos,
have invented the legal definitions of races. And it's not just the view of social scientists. You remember when the map of the human genome was unveiled at a White House ceremony in June 2000? President Bill Clinton famously declared, "I believe one of the great truths to emerge from this triumphant expedition inside the human genome is that in genetic terms, human beings, regardless of race, are more than 99.9 percent the same." And he might have added that that less than one percent of genetic difference doesn't fall into racial boxes. Francis Collins, who led the Human Genome Project and now heads NIH, echoed President Clinton. "I am happy that today, the only race we're talking about is the human race." Doctors are supposed to practice evidence-based medicine, and they're increasingly called to join the genomic revolution. But their habit of treating patients by race lags far behind. Take the estimate of glomerular filtration rate, or GFR. Doctors routinely interpret GFR, this important indicator of kidney function, by race. As you can see in this lab test, the exact same creatinine level, the concentration in the blood of the patient, automatically produces a different GFR estimate depending on whether or not the patient is African-American. Why? I've been told it's based on an assumption that African-Americans have more muscle mass than people of other races. But what sense does it make for a doctor to automatically assume I have more muscle mass than that female bodybuilder? Wouldn't it be far more accurate and evidence-based to determine the muscle mass of individual patients just by looking at them? Well, doctors tell me they're using race as a shortcut. It's a crude but convenient proxy for more important factors, like muscle mass, enzyme level, genetic traits they just don't have time to look for. But race is a bad proxy. In many cases, race adds no relevant information at all. It's just a distraction. But race also tends to overwhelm the clinical measures. It blinds doctors to patients' symptoms, family illnesses, their history, their own illnesses they might have -- all more evidence-based than the patient's race. Race can't substitute for these important clinical measures without sacrificing patient well-being. Doctors also tell me race is just one of many factors they take into account, but there are numerous medical tests, like the GFR, that use race categorically to treat black, white, Asian patients differently just because of their race. Race medicine also leaves patients of color especially vulnerable to harmful biases and stereotypes. Black and Latino patients are twice as likely to receive no pain medication as whites for the same painful long bone fractures because of stereotypes that black and brown people feel less pain, exaggerate their pain, and are predisposed to drug addiction. The Food and Drug Administration has even approved a race-specific medicine. It's a pill called BiDil to treat heart failure in self-identified African-American patients. A cardiologist developed this drug without regard to race or genetics, but it became convenient for commercial reasons to market the drug to black patients. The FDA then allowed the company, the drug company, to test the efficacy in a clinical trial that only included African-American subjects. It speculated that race stood in as a proxy for some unknown genetic factor that affects heart disease or response to drugs. But think about the dangerous message it sent, that black people's bodies are so substandard, a drug tested in them is not guaranteed to work in other patients. In the end, the drug company's marketing scheme failed. For one thing, black patients were understandably wary of using a drug just for black people. One elderly black woman stood up in a community meeting and shouted, "Give me what the white people are taking!" (Laughter) And if you find race-specific medicine surprising, wait until you learn that many doctors in the United States
han inventado definiciones legales de raza. No es solo la visión de los científicos sociales. ¿Recuerdan cuando se presentó el mapa del genoma humano en la Casa Blanca, en la ceremonia de junio de 2000? El presidente Bill Clinton dijo la célebre frase: "Creo que una de las grandes verdades que surgen de esta expedición triunfal al interior del genoma humano es decir que, en términos genéticos, los seres humanos, independientemente de la raza, somos en más de un 99,9 % lo mismo". Y podría haber agregado que esa diferencia de menos de 1 % no cae en las casillas raciales. Francis Collins, que dirigió el proyecto Genoma Humano y ahora dirige el NIH, parafraseó al presidente Clinton: "Estoy feliz de que hoy hablemos de una única raza, la raza humana". Los médicos se supone que deben practicar la medicina basada en evidencia, y se los llama cada vez a sumarse a la revolución genómica. Pero su costumbre de tratar pacientes por la raza está muy por detrás. Tomemos la estimación de la tasa de filtración glomerular, o TFG. Los médicos habitualmente interpretan la TFG, este indicador importante de la función renal, por la raza. Como pueden ver en esta prueba de laboratorio, exactamente el mismo nivel de creatinina, la concentración en la sangre del paciente, produce de forma automática una estimación de la TFG diferente en función de si el paciente es afroestadounidense o no. ¿Por qué? Me han dicho que tiene base en la suposición de que los afroestadounidenses tienen más masa muscular que las personas de otras razas. Pero ¿qué sentido tiene para un médico suponer automáticamente que yo tengo más masa muscular que esa mujer fisicoculturista? ¿No sería mucho más preciso y basado en evidencia determinar la masa muscular de cada paciente sencillamente examinándolos? Bueno, los médicos me dicen que usan la raza como un atajo. Es un intermediario crudo pero conveniente para factores más importantes como la masa muscular, el nivel de enzimas, los rasgos genéticos que simplemente no tienen tiempo para buscar. Pero la raza es un mal intermediario. En muchos casos, la raza no aporta información relevante en absoluto. Es solo una distracción. Pero la raza también suele abrumar las mediciones clínicas. Ciega a los médicos de los síntomas de los pacientes, de enfermedades familiares, de su historia, de las propias enfermedades que podrían tener... todo con más fundamento en evidencia que la raza del paciente. La raza no puede sustituir estas mediciones clínicas importantes sin sacrificar el bienestar del paciente. Los médicos me dicen que la raza es solo uno de muchos factores que tienen en cuenta, pero hay numerosas pruebas médicas, como la TFG, que usan la raza de manera categórica para tratar pacientes negros, blancos, asiáticos, de manera diferente solo por su raza. La medicina racial expone también a los pacientes de color a sesgos y estereotipos dañinos. Los pacientes negros y latinos tienen el doble de probabilidad de no recibir calmantes que los blancos por las mismas fracturas dolorosas de huesos largos, por causa del estereotipo de que las personas negras y marrones sienten menos dolor, exageran su dolor, y tienen predisposición a la adicción a fármacos. La Administración de Alimentos y Drogas aprobó un fármaco específico para la raza. Es una píldora llamada BiDil para tratar la insuficiencia cardíaca en pacientes autoidentificados como afro. Un cardiólogo desarrolló el fármaco sin distinción genética o de raza, pero se volvió conveniente por razones comerciales comercializar el medicamento para pacientes negros. La FDA luego permitió que la compañía farmacéutica probase la eficacia en ensayos clínicos que solo incluyeron a sujetos afroestadounidenses. Se especuló con que la raza actuara de intermediario para algún factor genético desconocido que afecta la enfermedad cardíaca o la respuesta al fármaco. Pero piensen en el mensaje peligroso que envía: que los cuerpos de las personas negras son tan deficientes que un medicamento probado en ellos no es garantía de que funcione en otros pacientes. Al final, falló el esquema de comercialización de la farmacéutica. Por un lado, los pacientes negros tomaron recaudos comprensibles en usar fármacos solo para negros. Una mujer negra de edad avanzada en una reunión de la comunidad gritó: "¡Denme lo que toman los blancos!" (Risas) Y si les sorprende la medicina específica por raza, esperen a saber que muchos médicos en Estados Unidos
still use an updated version of a diagnostic tool that was developed by a physician during the slavery era, a diagnostic tool that is tightly linked to justifications for slavery. Dr. Samuel Cartwright graduated from the University of Pennsylvania Medical School. He practiced in the Deep South before the Civil War, and he was a well-known expert on what was then called "Negro medicine." He promoted the racial concept of disease, that people of different races suffer from different diseases and experience common diseases differently. Cartwright argued in the 1850s that slavery was beneficial for black people for medical reasons. He claimed that because black people have lower lung capacity than whites, forced labor was good for them. He wrote in a medical journal, "It is the red vital blood sent to the brain that liberates their minds when under the white man's control, and it is the want of sufficiency of red vital blood that chains their minds to ignorance and barbarism when in freedom." To support this theory, Cartwright helped to perfect a medical device for measuring breathing called the spirometer to show the presumed deficiency in black people's lungs. Today, doctors still uphold Cartwright's claim the black people as a race have lower lung capacity than white people. Some even use a modern day spirometer that actually has a button labeled "race" so the machine adjusts the measurement for each patient according to his or her race. It's a well-known function called "correcting for race." The problem with race medicine extends far beyond misdiagnosing patients. Its focus on innate racial differences in disease diverts attention and resources from the social determinants that cause appalling racial gaps in health: lack of access to high-quality medical care; food deserts in poor neighborhoods; exposure to environmental toxins;
todavía usan una versión actualizada de una herramienta de diagnóstico desarrollada por un médico durante la esclavitud, una herramienta de diagnóstico levemente vinculada a justificar la esclavitud. El Dr. Samuel Cartwright se graduó en la Facultad de Medicina de la Universidad de Pensilvania. Hizo prácticas en el sur profundo antes de la Guerra Civil, y era un conocido experto en lo que entonces se llamó "medicina de negros". Él promovió el concepto de enfermedad racial, que las personas de distintas razas padecen enfermedades diferentes y atraviesan enfermedades comunes de manera diferente. Cartwright argumentaba en los años 1850 que la esclavitud era beneficiosa para las personas negras por razones médicas. Afirmaba que como los negros tenían menor capacidad pulmonar que los blancos, el trabajo forzado era bueno para ellos. Escribió en una revista médica: "Es la vital sangre roja que se envía al cerebro la que libera sus mentes cuando están bajo el control del blanco, y es la falta de suficiencia de vital sangre roja lo que encadena sus mentes a la ignorancia y la barbarie en libertad". Para sostener esta teoría, Cartwright ayudó a perfeccionar un dispositivo médico para medir la respiración, llamado espirómetro, para mostrar la presunta deficiencia en los pulmones de los negros. Hoy, los médicos todavía confirman la alegación de Cartwright de que los negros, como raza, tienen menor capacidad pulmonar que los blancos. Algunos incluso usan un espirómetro modernizado que en realidad tiene un botón con la etiqueta "raza" para ajustar la máquina a la medición para cada paciente, según su raza. Es una función bien conocida llamada "corrección por raza". El problema de la medicina racial va mucho más allá del diagnóstico erróneo. Hace hincapié en diferencias raciales innatas en la enfermedad, distrae la atención y los recursos de los determinantes sociales que causan brechas raciales atroces en la salud: la falta de acceso a la atención médica de alta calidad; desiertos de alimentos en los barrios pobres; exposición a toxinas ambientales;
high rates of incarceration; and experiencing the stress of racial discrimination. You see, race is not a biological category that naturally produces these health disparities because of genetic difference. Race is a social category that has staggering biological consequences, but because of the impact of social inequality on people's health. Yet race medicine pretends the answer to these gaps in health can be found in a race-specific pill. It's much easier and more lucrative to market a technological fix for these gaps in health than to deal with the structural inequities that produce them. The reason I'm so passionate about ending race medicine isn't just because it's bad medicine. I'm also on this mission because the way doctors practice medicine continues to promote a false and toxic view of humanity. Despite the many visionary breakthroughs in medicine we've been learning about, there's a failure of imagination when it comes to race. Would you imagine with me, just a moment: What would happen if doctors stopped treating patients by race? Suppose they rejected an 18th-century classification system and incorporated instead the most advanced knowledge of human genetic diversity and unity, that human beings cannot be categorized into biological races? What if, instead of using race as a crude proxy for some more important factor, doctors actually investigated and addressed that more important factor? What if doctors joined the forefront of a movement to end the structural inequities caused by racism, not by genetic difference? Race medicine is bad medicine, it's poor science and it's a false interpretation of humanity. It is more urgent than ever to finally abandon this backward legacy and to affirm our common humanity by ending the social inequalities that truly divide us. Thank you. (Applause) Thank you. Thanks. Thank you.
altas tasas de encarcelamiento; y pasar por el estrés de la discriminación racial. Ya ven, la raza no es una categoría biológica que produce de manera natural estas disparidades en la salud debido a diferencias genéticas. La raza es una categoría social que tiene consecuencias biológicas asombrosas, pero debido al impacto de la inequidad social en la salud de las personas. Y la medicina racial finge que la respuesta a estas brechas en la salud puede encontrarse en una píldora específica para la raza. Es mucho más fácil y mucho más lucrativo comercializar una cura tecnológica para estas brechas en la salud que lidiar con las inequidades estructurales que las producen. La razón por la que me apasiona terminar con la medicina racial no es solo porque es mala medicina. Estoy en esta misión porque la forma en que los médicos practican la medicina sigue promoviendo una visión falsa y tóxica de la humanidad. A pesar de tantos avances visionarios que conocemos en la medicina, hay una falta de imaginación cuando se trata de la raza. ¿Imaginarían conmigo, por un momento, que pasaría si los médicos dejaran de tratar a los pacientes según la raza? Supongamos que rechazaran el sistema de clasificación del siglo XVIII e incorporaran en su lugar el conocimiento más avanzado de la unidad y diversidad genética humana, que los seres humanos no entramos en categorías raciales biológicas? ¿Y si en vez de usar la raza como un intermediario crudo de algunos factores más importantes, los médicos en realidad investigaran y abordaran ese factor más importante? ¿Y si los médicos se sumaran a la vanguardia de un movimiento para terminar con las desigualdades estructurales provocadas por el racismo, no por la diferencia genética? La medicina racial es mala medicina, es ciencia pobre y es una interpretación falsa de la humanidad. Es más urgente que nunca abandonar finalmente este legado del pasado y afirmar nuestra humanidad común poniendo fin a las inequidades sociales que realmente nos dividen. Gracias. (Aplausos) Gracias. Gracias. Gracias.